大家好 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Hi it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
SpaceX的猎鹰九号火箭——世界上第一款可复用火箭
SpaceX's Falcon 9 rocket, the world's first reusable rocket.
停一下!
Wait!
不对吧
No, it's not.
还记得航天飞机吗?
Do you remember the Space Shuttle?
航天飞机的轨道器和固体火箭助推器都是可复用的不是吗?
It had those Solid Rocket Boosters, and the Orbiter which were both reusable, weren't they?
今天我们就来谈谈 为何航天飞机无法实现真正意义的"可复用"
Well today we're going to talk about why the Space Shuttle failed to actually be reusable,
也引入一个更准确的表述 "可翻新"
and wound up being described with a more accurate word, refurbishable.
人们经常喜欢拿航天飞机的缺点
People often cite the shortcomings of the Space Shuttle,
去抨击SpaceX猎鹰九号一级火箭的复用操作
and are quick to point it to SpaceX's claims of the Falcon 9 booster being reusable.
所以今天我们来看看 航天飞机两次飞行之间要做哪些操作
So today we're going to look at what it takes to get the Space Shuttle operational between flights;
猎鹰九号两次飞行之间又要做哪些操作
what it takes to get a Falcon 9 operational between flights,
为何让SpaceX猎鹰九号一级火箭复飞的工作量比航天飞机少得多
and why SpaceX's first stage booster take much less of a beating than the Space Shuttle did.
顺便快速回顾一下
We'll also do a quick reminder
Falcon 9 Block 5
SpaceX在"猎鹰九号构型5"中使用了哪些技术
of what technologies SpaceX added to their Block 5 booster
来实现他们制造快速可复用火箭的目标
to hopefully achieve their goal of making a rapidly reusable rocket
让这款火箭无需大规模翻新就能重复使用十次
that can truly be reused 10 times before needing any kind of serious refurbishment.
我们走起吧!
Let's get started!
毫无疑问 "可复用"是如今航天界最热门的词
Reusable is definitely the hottest buzz word in the new space industry.
如果你不知道为何火箭复用能够彻底改变行业的游戏规则
If you don't know why a vehicle being reusable is such a massive game changer,
建议看看往期视频 《为何重型猎鹰很重要》
may I suggest checking out my video "Why does Falcon Heavy matter"
可以让大家更好理解火箭可复用能力的重要性
to help get a good perspective on why reusability matters.
长话短说就是 发射进太空的重量余量太小了
But long story short, the margins to get stuff to space are so thin,
把那么多东西射上天需要巨大的火箭
it takes a massive rocket to put anything substantial up there.
因此 安装回收装置去复用火箭的重量余量非常非常小
So unfortunately there's just too little margins left over to add additional hardware
to make a rocket reusable.
所以传统的航天发射超级超级昂贵
This makes spaceflight extremely, extremely expensive.
昂贵到把成本降到每千克"仅"1000美元都算便宜的!
As in, so expensive we're hoping to someday see costs come down to "just a $1000" per kilogram!
想象一下你在地球上遇到了这种水平的运费
Yeah, imagine those shipping costs down here on Earth.
喂 我订个现代伊兰特 2011款的轮胎要多少钱啊?
Hi there, I'm calling to get a quote for some new tires for my 2011 Hyundai Elantra.
废话 当然是GT款
Yes of course it's the GT model.
最近一直跑秋名山来着 所以轮胎该换了
I did some really cool drifting and so that's why the tires are bad.
所以轮胎要多少钱啊?
How much would the new tires be?
才400刀?
Oh $400?
运费呢?
How much for shipping?
三万六?!
$36000!
但每千克1000美元的价格 相比以前商业航天的报价也几乎是包邮了
And that would actually be a steal compared to the historically astronomical prices of getting space hardware into space.
就算是历史最低价 每千克也要3000美元左右
Even the cheapest dollar to kilogram ratio is around the $3000 per kilogram mark,
多亏了猎鹰九号和重型猎鹰压下来的价位
thanks to the Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy.
幸好地球上送快递 火箭不是刚需
It's a good thing rocket delivery isn't the standard here on Earth.
因此 火箭复用的概念出来了
So here's where reusability comes in.
其实基础原理很好懂
It's honestly fundamental!
毕竟火箭的发动机都要数百万美元
Of course! Why throw away super expensive multi-million dollar engines
更别说还有箭身和一大堆零件
and a massive fuselage and all that extra stuff,
若能回收复用 何乐而不为?
when you could just reuse it, right?
很好理解
I mean duh!
航天飞机的最初愿景正是如此
Well that was the original idea for the Space Shuttle.
事实上 早在人类登月之前 NASA就已经开始寻求可复用的火箭了
Believe it or not NASA was seeking a reusable launch vehicle before we even put humans on the moon.
最初的研究始于1968年
The original studies began in 1968,
比阿姆斯特朗在月球上那著名的一步 早了差不多十个月
some 10 months before Neil Armstrong famously took the first steps on the moon.
事实上 航天飞机首飞成员约翰·杨
As a matter of fact one of the first people to fly the Space Shuttle, John Young
是在月球漫步的时候接到航天飞机项目获批的消息
was walking on the moon when he got news of the Shuttle.
-正好我告诉你个好消息
- This looks like a good time for some good news here.
白宫昨天277票对60票通过了航天预算审批
The House passed the space budget yesterday, 277 to 60,
其中包括航天飞机的预算
which includes the votes for the Shuttle.
- 太棒了!
- That's wonderful, wonderful.
- Tony我跟你说 身为美国人真好啊 向祖国致敬
- Tony, again I'll say it, with that salute I'm proud to be an American.
多好的项目 多好的地方 多好的经历!
I'll tell you, what a program and what a place and what an experience.
-嗯 是啊是啊
- Yeah, and I'll say it too.
- 我觉得也是 我们国家太需要航天飞机了
- So am I, country needs that Shuttle mighty bad.
航天飞机带着大家的期待 时间快进到50年后的今天
So with all the excitement leading up to the Shuttle, fast forward 50 years to today,
人们现在对航天飞机的态度好像不那么好了
and the Space Shuttle has kind of a bad taste in our mouths.
发射成本极其昂贵 安全性也很差
It wound up being terribly expensive, pretty dangerous,
它发射成本超过了其他任何火箭
and actually more expensive than just about any other way to get into space,
不过有些操作只能让航天飞机上 所以倒也不是一无是处
although it could do things that no other launch vehicle could do.
那么 一群世界上最聪明的大脑设计出来的航天器
So with some of the greatest minds working on the Shuttle,
为何没能兑现承诺 降低发射成本呢?
why did it fail its promise of bringing the cost down?
SpaceX是没有吸取历史的教训 还是打算改写历史?
Is SpaceX doomed to repeat history or has a lot changed in 50 years?
首先 对比一下两者的回收方式
So first, let's look at the recovery methods of each system.
差别相当大
They're quite different.
航天飞机依靠降落伞和升力体机身来回收各部分
The Space Shuttle utilized both parachutes and a lifting body to recover hardware.
按顺序了解下都回收什么
Let's go in order of what was recovered,
首先是固体火箭助推器
so starting with the Solid Rocket Boosters,
起飞大约两分钟后抛弃
which were jettisoned around two minutes into flight.
3000MPH
助推器与航天飞机分离时速度大概是4800km/h
The boosters separate while traveling around 4800 kilometers an hour or 3000 miles an hour,
30英里
分离高度大约45公里
at an altitude of around 45 kilometers or 30 miles.
40英里
之后靠惯性继续飞到大约65公里的高度
And due to their velocity they continue to coast upward to their highest point of around 65 kilometers or 40 miles.
因此 一个有趣的知识点
Just a fun note that does means the SRBs
航天飞机的固推从来没有飞出卡门线——公认的太空的边界
never actually make it above the Karman line or the commonly agreed upon boundary of space.
要记住这点
So keep that in mind.
固推下落 穿过大气
The boosters fall back through the atmosphere,
在4786米的高度按顺序放出一组降落伞
and start popping a sequence of parachutes at exactly 4786 meters or 15704 feet.
先是引导伞 然后是减速伞
Eventually after a pilot chute, and a drogue chute,
最后放出三个主伞
the three main parachutes deploy,
然后以相对平稳的速度溅落海面
and splish splash the booster down relatively softly in the ocean.
另一边的轨道器 速度就快多了
The Orbiter on the other hand is traveling much, much faster,
所以它的回收过程……就更加……火急火燎了
and its recovery, like all orbital things, is a lot hotter.
着陆前一小时 轨道器调姿转身
About one hour before touchdown, the Orbiter turns around,
发动机向前 机头向后
and faces away from its direction of travel or prograde.
启动轨道机动系统 降低1%的速度
It fires up its orbital maneuvering system or OMS and slows down 1%.
对 你没听错 只减速1%
Yep, that's it, only about 1%!
300英里               28英里
足够将轨道器的轨道近地点从480公里降低到45公里
And that's enough to lower its orbit from about 480 kilometers or 300 miles
down to just 45 kilometers or 28 miles at its lowest point.
厉害吧!
That's crazy!
变轨之后 轨道器还要再转向机头朝前 保持约40度的再入攻角
The Orbiter then turns back around so it can reenter at about a 40 degree angle.
接下来就靠大气层了
Now it's time for the atmosphere to do its work.
此时航天飞机还在轨道上滑行
The Orbiter is absolutely cruising at this point.
17000MPH
速度仍然高达27000km/h
It's still traveling around 27000 kilometers an hour or 17000 miles an hour,
接着 空气分子开始撞击机身 产生极大的摩擦力
the Orbiter begins to hit air molecules and starts to build up a ton of friction,
从而产生大量热量
and therefore a ton of heat.
3000°F
轨道器最热的地方 甚至能烧到1650°C!
The Orbiter will reach temperatures of 1650 degrees Celsius or 3000 degrees Fahrenheit!
烫烫烫
Ouch!
而航天飞机的轨道器有4套不同的热防护系统
But luckily, the Orbiter is covered with four different types of thermal protection.
机翼前缘有强化碳-碳复合材料
It has reinforced carbon-carbon on the leading edges;
机腹与前部有共计24177到31088块不等的绝热瓦 取决于机型
then there were between 24177 and 31088 tiles, depending on the Orbiter
on the underside and front of the vehicle;
载荷舱门 上翼面与机身有白色Nomex绝热毯覆盖
then there is white Nomex blankets on the upper payload bay doors, the upper wing and fuselage;
还有少量同为白色的表面绝热瓦用于保护相对低温的区域
and a few white surface tiles for low temperature areas as well.
在12分钟时间内 航天飞机表面会被炽热的电离气体覆盖
For 12 minutes, the Shuttle had so much hot ionized gases surrounding the vehicle,
无法与外界通信 也就是黑障区
it caused a full radio blackout.
具体的再入过程 请看av411183489
最终 在几分钟的大气减速与计算机制导下的"S型转弯"后
Eventually, after several minutes of atmospheric drag and some computer guided S-turns,
航天飞机的速度减慢了很多
the Shuttle bleeds off a lot of its velocity.
25英里
当距离着陆点40千米时
Once it's about 40 kilometers or 25 miles downrange,
原文是"姿态为-20度" 实际应指下滑道的角度
航天飞机进近的下滑角是18-20度
航天飞机的下滑角调整为负20度
the commander drops the nose to minus 20 degrees,
民航客机在一般的机场 进近下滑角是3度
这个角度是正常客机下滑角的近7倍
that's almost seven times steeper than a commercial airliner,
下降率是正常客机近20倍!
and it's still traveling 20 times faster.
不过最后落地的姿态倒是没太大区别 只是速度稍微快了一点点
Finally the Shuttle lands like a traditional jetliner only a little quicker,
220MPH                                2.8英里
以350km/h的速度落在足足4.5公里长的跑道上
touching down at 350 kilometers an hour or 220 miles an hour on a 4.5 kilometer or 2.8 mile long runway.
5英尺
这个长度的跑道 光是因为地球表面弧度就由1.5米的鼓包了!
That runway's actually so long that there's over a one and a half meter or over 5 feet in relative height difference
between the ends of the runway due to the curve of the Earth!
厉害吧!
That's crazy!
挺不容易的 欢迎航天飞机回家
It's quite the journey! Welcome home, Space Shuttle.
我们再快速回顾一下猎鹰九号是如何回收的
So now, let's do a quick rundown on how a Falcon 9 is recovered.
其实已经讲过很多次很深了
I've covered this topic a few times, more in depth,
还有哪里不懂的话 欢迎回看往期视频《SpaceX如何回收猎鹰九号》
so if you have any questions remaining check out my video "How SpaceX lands the Falcon 9".
猎鹰九号升空约2分40秒后 一级关机
At around two minutes and 40 seconds into flight the Falcon 9 shuts down its main engines,
也就是经常听到的"MECO"
called MECO or main engine cut off.
继续滑行几秒后
It coasts for a moment,
一级会与二级分离
and then the first stage lets go of the second stage for stage separation.
5000MPH
此时 猎鹰九号的一级速度是8000km/h
At this point the Falcon 9 is traveling up to 8000 kilometers an hour or almost 5000 miles an hour
40英里
高度是65千米
at an altitude of 65 kilometers or 40 miles.
几乎是航天飞机固推分离速度的两倍
Quick note, that's about twice as fast as the Space Shuttle's rocket boosters.
接着 一级火箭会用氮气调姿发动机做一个翻转机动 让发动机朝前
The first stage quickly performs a flip maneuver with its nitrogen thrusters to point its engines prograde.
然后 根据任务不同
Then, depending on the mission,
一级可能会点燃9台发动机中的三台 进行返场点火
the booster may ignite 3 of its 9 engines and do a boost back burn if it's going to land back at land.
如果剩余的燃料不够返场点火
But there might not be enough margins left over to do the boost back burn.
就跳过返场点火 一级火箭继续沿着弹道滑行
In that case it's omitted and the Falcon 9 continues on its ballistic trajectory
继续飞离发射场 飞向回收用的无人船
away from the launch pad and heads towards the drone ship,
基于任务需求 回收船早已在回收区域等候
that's been precisely placed based on each mission profile.
不过无论飞向哪里 一级火箭的滑行最高高度
But in either case the booster will coast up to its highest point,
62英里
通常都会超过100公里高的卡门线
typically over the Karman line or 100 kilometers or 62 miles.
换言之 至少有那么一瞬间 一级火箭会进入太空
In other words the booster gets to hang out in space for a minute or so!
真羡慕啊 我也想去
Lucky, I wanna go.
34英里
等一级下降到55公里高空时
Around 55 kilometers or 34 miles in altitude,
一级火箭会点燃9台中的3台发动机 执行再入点火
the Falcon 9 will light up three of its nine Merlin engines as it reenters the atmosphere.
以此来降低下降速度
It does this to slow itself down,
同时还会形成一个"力场"
and it actually creates a literal force field around itself,
保护它不会在再入时烧毁
so it can survive reentry.
在大约20秒的再入点火后
After around 20 seconds of reentry burn,
一级火箭的速度会减少30%到40%
the booster scrubs off 30 to 40% of its velocity,
保证后续下降中大气摩擦热量不会再对箭体构成威胁
which is enough to withstand the remaining heat as the atmosphere gets thicker and thicker.
并借气动减速 再降低剩余60%到70%的速度
The atmosphere will then take off another 60 to 70% of the remaining velocity,
620MPH
直到速度降低到仅1000km/h时
until the booster is only traveling about 1000 kilometers an hour or 620 miles an hour.
一级火箭一台或三台梅林发动机 进行最终的着陆点火
Then it lights up one or three of its Merlin engines to perform the final landing burn,
这一步需要非常精准的时间控制
which it needs to time perfectly.
因为就算只开一台发动机保持着最小的推力
Even with just one of the nine engines running at its minimum throttle,
也大到无法让火箭悬停
the booster still has too much thrust to hover.
所以如果火箭在着陆前就没有垂直速度了
So if the vehicle stops before it hits the ground,
它就会再一次飞走
it'll actually start going back up.
回收了个寂寞
Yeah, that's not good.
这个精确点火时机的机动 称为"Hoverslam"或者"自杀式点火"
This needs to be perfectly timed in a maneuver called the hover-slam or suicide burn.
然后放下着陆腿 猎鹰九号一级缓缓着陆
Then the landing legs deploy and the Falcon 9 softly touches down.
但愿如此吧……
Well, hopefully.
这时有人会问 为何SpaceX不能像航天飞机固推那样使用降落伞?
So before we move on, let's really quick remind you why the Falcon 9 doesn't use parachutes,
like the Space Shuttle SRBs did?
原因有如下几条
Well there's a few reasons,
已经有很多视频解释过了 所以在此简单罗列一下
and I'm just gonna breeze through these since I've done many videos about this,
将来有机会的话 可能还会有更深入的讲解
and I probably still need to do a more dedicated and updated video about it.
《天天太空人》之 猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收的七大理由!
So here's Everyday Astronaut's top seven reasons why SpaceX doesn't use parachutes to land the Falcon 9!
第一 SpaceX在猎鹰九号遥一遥二任务中尝试过降落伞回收
One: SpaceX tried to use parachutes on the first two Falcon 9 missions to recover the booster.
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
但可惜 一级火箭的速度是航天飞机助推器的两倍
Unfortunately, the booster is going about twice as fast as the SRBs,
降落伞无法承受更多的负荷
and the parachutes couldn't survive the extra forces.
第二 火箭本身有用于减速的发动机 为何放着不用?
Two: The rocket already has engines capable of slowing down why not use them?
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
直升机需要降落伞来降落么?
Does a helicopter need a parachute to land?
不需要 因为直升机有螺旋桨有发动机啊!
No it has an engine and a propeller already!
第三 月球与火星着陆无法使用降落伞
Three: You can't land a large rocket on Mars or the moon with a parachute,
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
3. 月球与火星着陆无法使用
提前练手反推着陆!
火星大气太少 月球没有大气
the atmosphere is too thin or nonexistent.
不如现在就开始学习反推着陆 肯定能用上!
So you'd better start practicing propulsive landings now and get good at 'em!
第四 火箭再入大气之前 无论如何都要先减速
Four: The rocket needs to slow down before it hits the atmosphere to survive reentry anyway.
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
3. 月球与火星着陆无法使用
提前练手反推着陆!
4. 再入大气前
降落伞无法使火箭减速
还记得"再入点火"吧?
Remember that whole reentry burn thing?
而降落伞在大气层之外可没啥效果
Yeah, a parachute can't work very well before it's in the atmosphere,
因此只能用火箭发动机减速
so rocket engines are the only way to go.
第五 降落伞与附带系统
Five: Parachutes and the supporting system,
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
3. 月球与火星着陆无法使用
提前练手反推着陆!
4. 再入大气前
降落伞无法使火箭减速
5. 降落伞会增加重量
让箭体不仅能压缩 还要能拉伸
that would allow the fuselage to get stretched and not just compressed
会给火箭增加死重
would just add otherwise dead weight.
第六 虽然降落伞也不是不能控制
Six: Parachutes, although steerable
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
3. 月球与火星着陆无法使用
提前练手反推着陆!
4. 再入大气前
降落伞无法使火箭减速
5. 降落伞会增加重量
6. 降落伞无法控制
火箭精确着陆
但远没有格栅舵 冷气推进器与发动机摆动那样精准
are not nearly as precise as grid fins cold gas thrusters and an engine gimbal.
SpaceX尝试用滑翔伞回收整流罩时 就发现了这点
SpaceX is finding this out the hard way as they tried to catch their fairings under steerable parafoils.
第七 火箭发动机掉海里很不好
Seven: Splashing down is bad mkay.
《天天太空人》
猎鹰九号不用降落伞回收
七大理由
1. 他们试过 没成功
2. 火箭有发动机可用于减速
3. 月球与火星着陆无法使用
提前练手反推着陆!
4. 再入大气前
降落伞无法使火箭减速
5. 降落伞会增加重量
6. 降落伞无法控制
火箭精确着陆
7. 海水对发动机等部件
非常不友好
精密的液体火箭发动机与海水天生八字不合
Salt water and precise liquid rocket engine don't mix very well.
可以说 这是个非常重要的改良
So that's actually a great place to transition.
那么现在 我们回收了航天飞机
Okay, so now that we recovered the reusable parts of the Space Shuttle
也回收了猎鹰九号的一级
and the first stage of the Falcon 9.
接下来 它们需要怎样的工序才能再次发射呢?
What did they do to prepare them for reflight?
先说说航天飞机
Let's start with the Space Shuttle.
如何才能让它重新站上发射台?
What did it take to get one back to the launch pad?
第一件事是派潜水员 用巨型塞子把溅落的固推底部密封
After splashdown, the boosters were sealed up by scuba divers with a giant plug
然后排空里面的水 再用拖船把固推水平拖回肯尼迪航天中心
where they drained the water so it could be towed back to Kennedy Space Center.
一枚固推的海上回收需要18人
Each booster required a crew of 18 for ocean recovery.
航天飞机有两个固推 所以一共36人
The Space Shuttle obviously had two boosters so that's 36 people on booster recovery.
然后助推器会被拆解 送往犹他州Promontory 进行清理 重喷漆
Then the boosters are disassembled and sent out to Promontory, Utah to be cleaned, paint stripped, repainted,
检查状况 并重新装填固推药剂
inspected and reloaded with solid propellant.
再运回肯尼迪航天中心
Then they go back to Kennedy Space Center
在"联合空间联盟总装与翻新站"进行组装
for assembly at the United Space Alliance Assembly and Refurbishment Facility.
很贴切的名字
I like the name of that place.
每枚固推的四段组装好后 会换上新的点火器
The four segments in each booster are then mated to a new igniter,
前段 头锥 尾裙部等乱七八糟的东西
forward segment, nose cap, aft skirt and frustum, whatever that is.
基本上 真正"复用"的也就只有外壳了
So basically just the casing was actually truly reused.
我觉得叫"翻新"肯定更加准确
I definitely think refurbished is the right word here
毕竟是把整个固推的皮扒下来只剩骨头
considering they stripped it down to the bare metal each time,
然后再拿到翻新站里去处理
and taken to a place called the Refurbishment Facility.
所以固推并不能算真正意义上的"可复用"
Okay, so the boosters aren't at all what I'd call reusable,
那轨道器呢?
but how about the Orbiter?
怎样才能让轨道器重新上天呢?
What's it take to actually get that thing reflying?
着陆之后 由150人组成的训练有素的小组 以及25辆任务定制的车辆
After touching down a highly trained crew of 150 people and 25 specially designed vehicles
会来到航天飞机旁边
head out to intercept the vehicle.
首先检查易爆与有毒气体
They do safety checks for explosives and toxic gases,
然后协助航天乘组撤离
helped the crew exit the Orbiter,
最后再把航天飞机拖进轨道器处理站
and eventually they tow it to the Orbiter Processing Facility.
29000平方英尺
然后在这个2700平方米的机库里
Once inside the 2700 square meter or 29000 square foot hangar,
进行约125天的检修工作
the Shuttle would be processed for approximately 125 days.
会有超过115个多层平台先后环绕航天飞机
More than 115 multi-level platforms would surround the vehicle,
让工程师们检查其600万个部件
so engineers could check six million parts.
六百万!
Six million parts!
没搞错?
What?
首先 技术人员会穿着防护服去清理机身
But first technicians would don hazmat suits to clean the vehicle
去掉一切残余的有毒或自燃物质
of any remaining toxic and hypergolic elements.
然后拆除轨道机动系统与前部反作用控制系统组件
Then they would remove the Orbital Maneuvering System pods, and the Forward Reaction Control Systems modules
方便检修及测试
to be repaired and retested.
然后 团队还会拆掉3台RS-25主发动机
Then crews would take off all three of the Space Shuttle's main engines, or RS-25s.
RS-25即使在现在也是非常厉害的发动机
These babies are still incredible engines,
效率仍然是第一梯队的
some of the most efficient engines ever made.
但是发动机每次发射之间都要进行海量的检查与翻新
But they required a healthy amount of inspection and refurbishment between each flight.
每台发动机有五万个零部件
Each engine had 50000 parts,
其中约七千个是寿命有限 需要不定期换新的
and about 7000 of which were life-limited and occasionally had to be replaced.
2002年 肯尼迪航天中心接手了发动机的组装工作
In 2002, Kennedy Space Center took over assembly tasks of the engines
不用为了翻新发动机而运来运去了
instead of sending them out for refurbishment.
而翻新航天飞机最最重量级的任务
But perhaps the biggest and most daunting task of the Space Shuttle
则是检修那几万块一碰就坏的绝热瓦
was inspecting the thousands and thousands of fragile silica tiles on the bottom of the Orbiter.
前面提到 航天飞机根据型号不同 会有24177到31088片绝热瓦
There were between 24177 and 31088 tiles, depending on the Orbiter.
每一片都是独一无二的
Every single one was unique,
必须逐个仔细检查 坏了就换
and had to be carefully inspected and if damaged, replaced.
当然还有航电设备 载荷舱 液压操纵面 等等
And of course, all the avionics, the payload bay the hydraulic control surfaces etc, etc
它们也需要在每次飞行后仔细检查
were carefully checked out between each flight as well.
算下来 航天飞机每次飞行需要耗费大约65万工时
In total, the Space Shuttle required no less than 650000 hours of labor between each flight.
按平均每人每小时工资25美元
Say the average person made $25 an hour,
这个数字对这些训练有素的技术工种已经非常保守了
which I'm sure is kind of conservative for a highly trained technician,
航天飞机每次飞行耗费的人力成本大约是1600万美元
the cost of human labor to get a Space Shuttle ready for launch would be around 16 million dollars!
别忘了 这都是保守估计
And again, that's being fairly conservative.
早些年的时候还好点
But it wasn't always this way.
因为在1986年挑战者号事故之前
Actually, before the Challenger accident in 1986,
航天飞机的检查与翻新工作远没有这么多
the Shuttle went through much less refurbishment and checks.
在那之前 两次飞行之间大概只需后来1%的工时
So few in fact, it may have seen as little as almost 1% the amount of labor hours between flights.
但在挑战者号事故之后
But after the Challenger accident,
NASA把航天飞机的所有翻新流程都改了
NASA changed the entire process of getting the Space Shuttle flight ready,
几乎是提着灯去检查航天飞机每一寸角落
and wound up going over every single inch with a fine-tooth comb.
毕竟人命攸关的事 小心驶得万年船
That's probably a good thing when you're dealing with human life.
再往后 到了1989年 为了方便航天飞机的总装
Oh and lastly, after 1989, to get the Shuttle ready,
NASA给它配了一辆76轮的运输车
it was placed on top of the Orbiter Transfer System,
用来把航天飞机从轨道器处理站运往火箭总装大楼
a 76 wheel transporter, to take it from the OPF, to the Vehicle Assembly building,
这里安装外挂燃料箱与两枚固体火箭助推器
to be mated with the external tank and the Solid Rocket Boosters.
有趣的是 现在这辆76轮运输车已经属于SpaceX了
Fun fact, SpaceX now owns the Orbiter Transfer System to transport their boosters!
那么 现在问题来了
Okay, now time for the big question.
猎鹰九号又要经历怎样的过程才能再次发射呢
What does it take to get a Falcon 9 booster back to the launch pad?
首先我想说的是 以下均为猜测
Let me start off by saying a lot of this is speculation,
由于SpaceX并未公布火箭准备工作的具体内容
since SpaceX doesn't make public exactly what goes into preparation,
不过我们可以先了解一下他们已经做了什么
but let's give a rundown on what they have done,
以及未来打算做什么
and what things they will be doing.
首先 如果是海上回收
So first off, if it landed on the drone ship,
会有一个小型机器人出动 固定住一级火箭
a little robot actually comes out and grabs onto the booster and hangs on to it,
免得……
so this doesn't happen…
然后由两艘船 大约10位工作人员将火箭拖回
It's then transported back by a support crew of around 10 and two ships.
如果是陆地回收
But if the booster lands on land,
会有吊车把一级火箭放上运输车
the booster is picked up by a crane and put onto their transporter.
在猎鹰九号前几年的回收中
For the first few years of the Falcon 9 reuse,
火箭会运往加州Hawthorne进行翻新
the booster were shipped back to Hawthorne for the refurbishment.
不过SpaceX正在卡纳维拉尔角建造新的火箭翻新设施
But SpaceX is building a booster refurbishment facility at the cape.
第一枚成功回收助推器 来自2015年12月21日的OG2任务
The first booster to ever land on December 21, 2015 for the OG2 mission
那枚火箭后来被彻底拆解研究
was extensively torn down and inspected.
毕竟这是SpaceX第一次回收完整的火箭
Since this was the first booster that SpaceX actually caught in one piece,
他们需要仔细检查 看看箭体情况是否完好
they had to check their work and see if it actually came out okay.
最初的13枚复用箭 或者说非构型5的火箭
On the first 13 reused boosters, or non-Block 5 boosters,
我们知道SpaceX更换了喷管后面的隔热罩与隔热毯
we know SpaceX changed out the heat shields and blankets behind the exhaust nozzles.
我们知道在高热量的任务中会维修或更换格栅舵
We know they had to fix and repair the grid fins on the extra hot missions.
我们知道他们需要对火箭进行大量的检查
We know they had to do a lot of inspections on the vehicle,
还知道他们会用X光检查一级火箭箭体情况是否正常
but they also had to run an X-ray along the booster to ensure the fuselage is still good to go.
我听说 构型3或构型4的一级翻新工作大约需要一千到一万工时
Now I've heard speculations of between 1000 to 10000 human hours of labor
for the turnaround of the Block 3 and Block 4 boosters.
但就算是最糟的猜测
And say this is terribly conservative.
需要100000工时才能搞定
Say it's actually 100000 hours of labor,
那也还不到航天飞机轨道器的六分之一
that'd still be over six times less labor than the Space Shuttle Orbiter.
猎鹰九号要检查的系统比轨道器少
The Falcon 9 has much less systems to check over than the Orbiter,
因此可以认为 猎鹰九号翻新工作耗费的工时要少得多
so I think it's pretty safe to assume there's a lot less labor hours required to prepare it for reflight.
我们知道SpaceX的目标是让新的构型5猎鹰九号
We know SpaceX has a goal with their new Block 5 Falcon 9
可以在24至48小时内重新发射
to see it land and refly within 24 to 48 hours with
每次飞行后只做简单的检查
nothing but inspections and checks between flights.
构型5的总体目标是在不进行翻新 只做小检查的情况下重复飞行10次
The overall goal of their new Block 5 booster is to be reflown 10 times
without any actual refurbishment, only inspections.
SpaceX从之前24次回收获取的经验设计出猎鹰九号构型5
They built Block 5 having learned the lessons from the 24 recoveries leading up to Block 5,
如果你对构型5的进化有兴趣的话
if you need a reminder of what's new with Block 5,
我也有个视频介绍了猎鹰九号构型5的改进之处
I have a video all about what Block 5 is and what has changed.
简单介绍下构型5的更新: 全箭防热层
A quick list of things that are new with the Block 5 is a thermal protective coating on the whole booster,
发动机旁液冷隔热罩
a liquid cooled heat shield by the engines,
焊接的环形发动机舱 一级8%的推力提升
a bolted Octaweb, 8% increase in thrust on the first stage,
升级后可收回的着陆腿 钛合金格栅舵
upgraded retractable landing legs, titanium grid fins,
升级的复合材料缠绕压力容器2.0
an upgraded COPV 2.0,
等等大量的升级 让这款火箭复用性更强
and a ton of tweaks that allow it to be even more reusable,
最重要的 获得载人的认证
and most importantly, rated for human flight.
所以为何猎鹰九号每次飞行后不需要进行翻修……
So how can the Falcon 9 booster actually be reflown without refurbishment?
真不需要吗?
Can it?
猎鹰九号和航天飞机区别何在?
What's so different about the Falcon 9 compared to the Space Shuttle?
先让猎鹰九号和航天飞机的固推进行对比
Well let's first compare it to the SRBs and see what it actually does differently.
首先 让固推直接溅落大海上
First off, the SRBs splashed down in salt water.
其实没多大实惠
That's not really a good thing.
固推其实就是一个超大的空壳
Solid Rocket Boosters are also basically giant empty canisters
每次飞行前要重新填满橡胶质地的固体药剂
that are loaded up with a rubber like solid propellant between each flight.
它和上万个零件的液体火箭发动机根本没法比
This is different than a liquid fueled rocket engine, that has say tens of thousands of parts.
液体火箭发动机要是泡在海水里
If a liquid engine were to be submerged in salt water,
我觉得后果不会太好
I don't think that'd be a good thing.
所以 关键的地方就在这里
So right there is probably the biggest thing,
让一级火箭降落在陆地 或者干燥的拖船甲板上
having a booster land on dry land or a dry ship deck
对复用性和翻新工程来说是很大的进步
is a huge leg up as far as reusability and refurbishment goes.
事实上 固推的翻新费用也非常昂贵
As a matter of fact the SRBs were so expensive to refurbish,
长远来看 把固推拆解运回去装药等一通操作
in the long run, it was more expensive to bring them back tear them down and all that
还不如造个新的来的便宜
than it was just to build new ones.
那猎鹰九号为何比航天飞机轨道器有更强的可复用性?
So why is the Falcon 9 booster more reusable than the Orbiter?
首先 轨道器不仅仅是一款火箭
Well first off, the Orbiter was not only a rocket,
它还是一艘能载7人的飞船
it was also a spaceship that carried up to seven people.
因此 驾驶舱 飞船内部 载荷舱等等 全都需要大量的检查工作
So a lot of work and check outs, went into the cockpit the interior, the payload bay etc, etc,
更别说轨道器的三台火箭发动机了
let alone the actual rocket engine portion of the Orbiter.
虽然RS-25参数非常棒 后来也做到了现场翻修
The RS-25 engine, although amazing and eventually refurbished on-site,
但想要重新上天 还是需要非常可观的工作量
still required an awful lot of work to fly again.
而SpaceX研发的梅林1D发动机 已经点火超过5600次了
The Merlin 1D engine that SpaceX has developed has been fired over 5600 times,
其设计目标就是只需最少的检查就能多次飞行
and is designed to be reflown and reused over and over with minimal inspections.
这个检查工作量有多少目前还不得而知 待会儿再讨论
How much, we don't really know yet but more on that in a second.
但猎鹰九号一级和航天飞机最大的不同是两者的再入速度
But perhaps the biggest difference between the Falcon 9 booster and the Space Shuttle Orbiter
is the velocity in which each one reenters.
对比下固推 猎鹰九号一级和轨道器的速度
Let's compare the velocities of the SRB, the Falcon 9 first stage and the Orbiter
就能理解它们各自不同的再入系统
to help understand why each one uses their given reentry system.
SRB速度上限也就4800km/h
The SRB never exceeds 4800 kilometers an hour,
也不会离开大气层
and it also stays lower in the atmosphere,
因此不需要为再入而提前减速
so it doesn't require any kind of slow down before it reenters,
没出过大气何来"再"入?
well because it never really exited in the first place.
而猎鹰九号的一级 最快能达到8000km/h
The Falcon 9 on the other hand goes from up to about 8000 kilometers an hour,
最慢也有5000km/h
down to as low as about 5000 kilometers an hour,
为了撑过再入热量 要提前使用发动机减速
in order to survive reentry using its retropropulsion.
以后一级回收时的最高速度应该也不会超出8000km/h多少
But it's safe to say it will probably never see much more than 8000 kilometers an hour.
轨道器的再入速度就快多了 有27000km/h
The Orbiter reenters at speeds of up to 27000 kilometers an hour,
而它会在高空稀薄大气中 慢慢减速
but it slowly bleeds off a lot of its speed in the upper atmosphere.
因此三者速度上的差距是非常大的
Wow Those are some pretty big differences in velocity.
因为猎鹰九号一级再入速度只有不到8000km/h
Since the Falcon 9 booster reenters at only 8000 kilometers an hour,
它经受的热量就只有轨道器的大概1/40
it experiences up to almost 40 times less heat compared to the Orbiter.
很奇怪对不对!
What? How can that be?
猎鹰九号一级的最大速度不超过轨道器的三分之一
Well, since the first stage of the Falcon 9 only gets up to at most about a third of orbital velocity,
而其产生的气动热量则远小于轨道器的1/3
it receives much less than just 1/3rd of the amount of heat.
航天器迎风面产生的热量与速度的平方成正比
The compressed gas on the leading edge of any vehicle will see heat increase by velocity squared,
而传导到航天器上的热量与速度的三次方成正比
but the thermal energy transferred to the rocket goes as velocity cubed!
所以如果航天器速度变快四倍
So that means if a vehicle is traveling four times faster,
它的迎风面会变热64倍!
the bow wave in front can get 64 times hotter!
因为速度是4倍 4的三次方 就是64倍的热量
'Cause that's four times faster, times four, so squared, times another four, cubed, so 64!
当然 这个计算是极度简化的
Now this is an oversimplification,
不过这也解释了航天飞机为了再入 机翼前缘要有碳-碳复合材料
but that's why the Space Shuttle needed those carbon-carbon leading edges,
机腹要贴满绝热瓦
and those silica tiles all over the bottom of it to survive reentry.
不仅如此 猎鹰九号的一级会在进入浓密大气前进行再入点火保护箭体
Not only that, but the Falcon 9 also does an a pretty significant retropropulsion burn
before it reenters, to ensure the vehicle can survive.
航天飞机没有这样的点火
The Space Shuttle didn't do any of this,
因为航天飞机靠的是它宽大的机身
because it relied on its large surface area
在高空稀薄大气中滑翔数分钟来缓慢减速
to slowly bleed the speed off for several minutes.
事实上 航天飞机要花接近10倍的时间来散发掉再入时产生的热量
As a matter of fact the Space Shuttle spent almost 10 times the amount of time
radiating heat off through reentry,
这也是其非烧蚀绝热瓦的工作原理
which is the key to how its non-ablative heat shield worked.
总的来说 猎鹰九号一级再入速度更慢 产生热量更少
So long story short, the first stage is going slow enough to not get crazy hot,
所以不需要太多的热防护系统
so it doesn't require nearly as much thermal protection.
应该可以认为 这样能避免大量的翻新工作
Therefore it's probably safe to say it doesn't require as much refurbishment, hopefully.
最后再来说说我的想法
So some final thoughts on all this.
首先 为什么我觉得猎鹰九号可以实现低价可复用
First off, the reason why I think the Falcon 9 will actually achieve reusability,
而航天飞机做不到
when the Space Shuttle couldn't
主要原因是SpaceX的工程理念
is mostly due to the engineering philosophy of SpaceX.
SpaceX的火箭不断修改进化的
They are constantly tweaking their rocket
用SpaceX生产部副总Andy Lambert的话说
to the point where according to SpaceX's VP of production, Andy Lambert.
"SpaceX从未制造 '两个完全相同的火箭'
SpaceX has never built any two vehicles identically,
这就是SpaceX的创新步伐"
such is the pace of innovation at SpaceX."
而航天飞机完全不是这样
Now this is quite different from the Space Shuttle,
总共只有五艘用于飞行
that had only only five operational vehicles,
30年间的更新也非常少
that changed very little in their 30 years of operation.
事实上 航天飞机的第一阶段只有哥伦比亚号的四次飞行
As a matter of fact, phase one of the Space Shuttle was only the first four flights of Columbia.
在这之后的改进就微乎其微了
After that, further development would be minimal.
而猎鹰九号 如果某项设计没达到预期
But with the Falcon 9, if an idea doesn't work out,
SpaceX完全可以在下一枚火箭制造的时候就做出修改
they can literally make that change on one of the next manufactured boosters.
如果改动较大 就放在下一构型中实现
And if it's a really big change they'll do that on the next Block iteration.
真要说的话 航天飞机也不是完全没有修改
The Space Shuttle's design didn't exactly freeze,
但其三十多年的服役周期里做出的修改
but it certainly didn't evolve nearly as much in 30 years,
实在是比猎鹰九号这8年来少太多了
as the Falcon 9 has in eight years.
可能有人认为SpaceX这8年步子迈得太大
Some might consider this much change reckless,
但考虑到其最终目的 是真正可复用的火箭
but considering the end goal is to actually have a reusable vehicle,
我还是更喜欢这样激进的策略
I'm really glad they're pushing this aggressively.
毕竟一辈子有几个三十年?
I just can't wait another 30 years.
最后可能还有人认为 SpaceX永远没法把复用成本降到能回本的程度
And lastly to those that think SpaceX won't be able to make it worth the cost of reflying,
或者质疑这样做到底有什么意义之类
or who question whether or not it'll be worth it for them,
但幸运的是 这没关系呀!
luckily for us, it really doesn't matter.
SpaceX是个私企
SpaceX is a private company,
影响他们抉择的主要因素 只有钱
They will only do what makes the most financial sense.
也许几年后他们会发现复用火箭回不了本
So if after a few years they look back and realize,
造新火箭还是比复用火箭省钱省事
it's more expensive to try to refly these things than it is to make a new one.
那为了赚钱大不了就不干了呗
I'm sure they'll stop doing so because they don't wanna lose money.
他们没有任何义务去强行让自己的火箭可复用
They don't owe it to anyone to reuse their rockets.
他们只是认为复用有搞头 觉得能省钱 能让利益最大化
It's only in their best interest to figure out how to do so so they can maximize profits.
这和航天飞机当年的处境完全不同
And that's just different than the Space Shuttle,
后者承载着整个国家对可复用性的希望
which had the weight of the entire nation's expectations to be reusable.
不管整套系统能不能达到预期效果
Whether or not the system put in place actually made sense,
咬着牙也得让它飞
it was too late.
怕国会老爷犯嘀咕 所以航天飞机也不敢做大的修改
There was no room for major changes per say,
since Congress would probably frown upon.
"我觉得这样改不行 咱还是别搞航天飞机了"
"Well this didn't work out, let's scrap the entire idea."
所以我个人觉得 今天这样一个创新的时代 材料学有了进步
So personally I think with this new age of innovation and materials,
软硬件也都在飞速发展
rapid evolution of hardware and software,
决策者只要坚持尝试 总能找到解决办法
and leadership that simply requires they keep trying until they figure it out.
我觉得我们已经有一只脚踏入可回收火箭 火箭航空化的大门了
I think we're finally entering a new era of reusable and airliner like rockets.
希望如此吧!
Hopefully!
所以大家怎么看?
So what are your thoughts?
火箭复用是近在咫尺了
Is actual reusability finally upon us,
还是认为SpaceX不行 人类要完?
or do you think we're still going to be stuck in refurbishment land?
大家还有什么想讨论的问题?
What other questions do you have?
欢迎在评论区留下见解 疑问 或者视频内容建议
Let me know your thoughts, questions, and video requests in the comments below!
感谢来自kNews频道的Lukas提供的动画
Thanks to Lukas from kNews for his amazing animations.
我一直很喜欢他的作品 很高兴可以合作制作一些动画
I've always been a fan of his work and was so happy to work with him on some of these visuals.
别忘了去看看他的频道
Be sure and check out his awesome channel,
里面有很多航天新闻与其他航天相关的话题
where he does updates on spaceflight news and other great spaceflight topics as well.
去看看吧! kNews
Check it out, kNews!
也感谢在Patreon上赞助我的大家
And of course I owe a huge thanks to my Patreon supporters
让本期与每一期《天天太空人》节目成为现实
for helping me make this and all other Everyday Astronaut content possible.
你们太厉害了
You guys are seriously amazing!
是你们激励我继续坚持做研究
And you help me stay sane during all these long bouts of research.
他们在我的独家Discord和Reddit子版块帮我写脚本做研究
They hang out in my exclusive discord and our exclusive subreddit to help me script and research.
如果你也想出一份力
If you wanna help contribute,
欢迎去下方链接支持一下
please visit patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
非常非常感谢
Thank you, seriously thank you.
和往常一样 本期音乐均为原创
As always, all the music in my videos is original.
可以去下方链接免费下载
Feel free to check it out for free at soundcloud.com/everydayastronaut.
记得分享给朋友哦
Tell a friend.
我这件衣服终于登上我的网店啦
Hey guess what? This ridiculous shirt is finally available in my web store,
还有各种其他有趣的商品 比如帽子 杯子
along with a lot of other fun things like hats, mugs,
火箭发射的海报之类的
prints of rocket launches or original other work,
各种有趣商品 欢迎前往下方链接
and lots of other fun stuff at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
祝大家购物愉快
Have fun.
感谢大家 就到这里了
Thanks everybody, that does it for me.
我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
把航天知识带给寻常百姓家~
bringing space down to Earth for everyday people.